# NathanMitchell



#### **Personal Information**

Nathan Mitchell B.S, M.S. Computer Science http://nathanmitchell.graphics

#### Contact

Email (Preferred): contact@nathanmitchell.graphics Tel: (608) 509-4176

## Programming Languages

**C++, C, Python**, x86 Assembly, Bash/Zsh Scripting, Java, Cobol

#### **Tools**

2015

2014

Electron, LaTeX, Blender, Renderman, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Premiere, Intel VTune

#### Miscellaneous Technologies

Ubuntu/Debian, RabbitMQ, Git/Mercurial Version Control, SQL, NodeJS, OpenGL

## Résumé

My name is Nathan Mitchell and I am a finishing PhD student at the University of Wisconsin - Madison and a member of the UW Visual Computing Lab. My primary academic interests include physics simulation for deformable objects, software optimization for heterogeneous hardware, and rendering. I enjoy working on large software systems, particularly in the design of elegant APIs for long term maintainability.

My advisor at the University of Wisconsin is Dr. Eftychios Sifakis. Before I began my graduate program, I attended the University of Edinboro in Pennsylvania for my undergraduate degree in computer science. I have also worked with the Math and Computer Science division of Argonne National Labs, where I helped develop software for managing cluster provisioning.

#### **Education**

2013–Today PhD. Computer Sciences
(est. completion: May. 2017)

Masters of Computer Sciences

University of Wisconsin - Madison

University of Wisconsin - Madison

University of Edinboro

# **Publications**

2017

H. Liu, N. Mitchell, M. Aanjaneya, J. Lowe-Power, M. Aanjaneya, E. Sifakis A Hierarchical Domain Decomposition Preconditioner for the Poisson Equation Optimized for Heterogeneous Platforms in proceedings of Supercomputing, 2017

2016 Presented at SIGGRAPH Asia 2016

H. Liu, N. Mitchell, M. Aanjaneya, E. Sifakis A scalable Schur-complement fluids solver for heterogeneous compute platforms in proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Asia, 2016

N. Mitchell, C. Cutting, T. King, A. Oliker, E. Sifakis A Real-Time Local Flaps Surgical Simulator Based on Advances in Computational Algorithms for Finite Element Models Plastic & Reconstructive Surgery. 137(2):445e-452e, February 2016., 2016

Presented at SCA 2016

In Submission

N. Mitchell, M. Doescher, E. Sifakis A Macroblock Optimization for Grid-Based Nonlinear Elasticity Eurographics/ACM SIGGRAPH Symposium on Computer Animation, 2016

Presented at SIGGRAPH 2015

N. Mitchell, C. Cutting, E. Sifakis GRIDiron: An Interactive Authoring and Cognitive Training Foundation for Reconstructive Plastic Surgery Procedures in proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH, 2015

Presented at SIGGRAPH Asia 2015

N. Mitchell, M. Aanjaneya, R. Setaluri, E. Sifakis Non-manifold Level Sets: A multivalued implicit surface representation with applications to self-collision processing in proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Asia, 2015

Presented at SCA 2014

R. Setaluri, Y. Wang, N. Mitchell, L. Kavan, E. Sifakis Fast Grid-Based Nonlinear Elasticity for 2D Deformations Eurographics/ACM SIGGRAPH Symposium on Computer Animation, 2014

Presented at SCA 2014

*M. Gao, N. Mitchell, E. Sifakis* **Steklov-Poincaré Skinning** Eurographics/ACM SIG-GRAPH Symposium on Computer Animation, 2014

T. Patterson, N. Mitchell, E. Sifakis Simulation of Complex Nonlinear Elastic Bodies using Lattice Deformers in proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Asia, 2012

# **Experience**

2012-Today University of Wisconsin - Madison

Madison, Wisconsin - USA

Research Assistant

For the past several years, I have been the lead developer on a virtual surgery project, which aims to provide a virtual authoring and practice tool for plastic surgeons.

2008-2010 Argonne National Laboratory

Lemont, Illinois - USA

Intern

I spent three summers developing management software for the Mathematics and Computer Science Group at Argonne National Laboratory. The first software package was a web form deployment system to assist the help desk support staff. The second project, named **Heckle**, was a cluster hardware provisioning system designed to provide on-demand operating system installations tailored to user requirements.

2005-2006 Intel

Hillsboro, Oregon - USA

Intern - Technician

For two summers I worked in the Intel's Hillsboro fabrication plant as a manufacturing technician for their 200mm production line. The experience provided me first hand insight into modern integrated circuit manufacturing processes.

### **Research Interests**

**Simulation** I am very interested in pursuing further work regarding the pairing of bio-medical topics and real-time simulation, particularly in the areas of deformable solids and plastic surgery. I consider my work at Wisconsin to be a solid first step, but with a large potential for future work.

**Parallel Computing** While there have been many different approaches taken over the years to make parallel computing easier for programmers to make use of, my experience has shown that there are still many hurdles to overcome, especially in the areas of hardware vectorization and optimal use of memory bandwidth on highly parallel heterogeneous systems. I remain interested in pursing new frameworks and design patterns for improving a programmer's quality of life when dealing with these problems.

**Framework Design** Designing and building system frameworks, while not typically considered glamorous from a academic research perspective, is something that I feel is critical to designing useful software. I have spent a great deal of effort during my prior projects to build maintainable and reusable components, which have paid dividends in later research efforts.

**Rendering** My experience here is mostly due to the needs of presenting the results of high resolution simulations through publications. However, the challenges in this area have caught my attention and I have a continued interest in how highly complex simulated scenes can still be rendered efficiently.

**Game Design** I have a fascination with game mechanics and how interesting design choices make for engaging entertainment for players. While recently my medium has been boardgames, I believe many aspects of good game design are shared between the physical and electronic realms.

# **Projects**

**Plastic Surgery Simulation** For the past five years, I have been developing a simulation system for performing plastic surgery operations virtually in a collaborative environment. Over the course of the project, I developed a new SIMD abstraction library for efficiently optimizing finite element numerical kernels, a novel strategy for storing level set geometry in non-manifold topology, and explored approaches for remote simulation, including using modern web technolo-

gies as front-end clients. My efforts, beyond the production of the software artifacts, resulted in five publications, local news coverage, and a currently active exploration of commercialization opportunities.

**Heckle** During the spring and summer of 2010, I was the lead developer for a cluster provisioning system named Heckle for Argonne National Laboratories. Heckle was designed to manage a collection of potentially heterogeneous compute nodes. The problem being addressed was that researchers often needed custom hardware (specific CPU, memory capacity, accelerator cards) for their projects, but didn't need it long enough to warrant a dedicated machine. Heckle provided users with a single point of access to request nodes matching specific requirements and dynamically provision the nodes with custom operating system images. By interacting with out-of-band management services, Heckle could remotely power cycle nodes and initiate re-installations without administrator intervention.

### References

PhD. Advisor **Eftychios Sifakis, PhD** Madison, WI - USA

University of Wisconsin Madison Email: sifakis@cs.wisc.edu

URL: http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~sifakis

PhD. Committee Court Cutting, MD Santa Barbara, CA - USA

Email: ccuttingmd@gmail.com URL: http://www.courtcuttingmd.com

PhD. Committee Mike Gleicher, PhD Madison, WI - USA

University of Wisconsin Madison Email: gleicher@cs.wisc.edu

URL: http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~gleicher